So, Boolean logic and Python, you might have heard this expression truthiness.
Truthiness is figuring out what expressions evaluate to true or false in Python,
and that's going to help us control the flow of our program.
Now, I have a little handy cheat sheet for you here at the top.
With integers, truthiness works a little bit differently than you might expect.
The truthiness of integers 0 is false, all other numbers that have a value are true,
including negative numbers.
For container types, like the list, the tuple, the set, the dictionary,
empty containers evaluate to false containers with items in them evaluate to true.
Now, the none or null type is always false.
There are also keyword arguments of true with a capital T and false with a capital F.
Now, sometimes truthiness is pretty obvious.
Is this true or false?
It's true, right?
I tried it the reverse way, that's false.
You can always figure out what truthiness your expression will have by calling Boo on it,
and Boo maps to the constructor for the built-in true or false.
So, I can call Boo with one, which is true, Boo with zero, which is false.
But I can also pass in some complex expressions here,
and it will let me know what the truthiness value of them is.
So, calling Boo on an empty list, false, putting some items into it is true.
Boo of none type is always false.
You can compare different items in Python with less than greater than less than or equals.
But there's also the double equals and the not equals.
So, double equals is quality.
And this is not equals.
Equality for different container types is a little bit interesting.
So, equality for lists will check for the items in the list.
So, let's say I have list one.
And list two, if I call list one equals list two, I'm checking for equality of the
contents, and I'm not asking is this the same exact list.
If you do want to check for, hey, are these lists pointing at the same variable?
That is with, you're going to use a different keyword called is the checks for identity.
Basically, asking to these points the same place in memory.
They don't, they're stored at different variables.
So, this is a little bit of a more advanced topic, but the reason that I'm introducing it
is because we have a lot of keywords in Python that we've seen, like true and false and none.
In order to check for equality with these keywords, we want to use the is keyword for to check for
identity, do these things point to the same place in memory and not with equality.
This is especially handy with none because
a empty list can evaluate to false.
So, if we want to differentiate between none and an empty list, we need to use the is keyword.
And we can say is x none. Oops. Sorry, x is none, and that is true.
If I ask, empty list is none, that is false. So, if you need to differentiate between the
truthiness of a none value or something that has a false truthiness, like an empty list or zero,
you're going to need to use that is keyword.
And same for true and false. So, don't do a equals true. If you want to know explicitly,
you can say a is true. Oops. I would need to define that and that will say true.
So, the difference between equality and identity.
There's also the and or and not statements in Python.
One of the great things about Python is that these statements are just English keywords.
And it kind of spells out like you would type a sentence for those of you who might come from Java,
or another language like you don't have to do this stuff like it's super hard to remember when
you're a beginner. So, I think having these keywords definitely helps out with learning Python.
And let's say a equals true and b equals true. And means are both of these values true.
Only return true when they're both true.
If one of the values is false, that will return false. Or means is are any of these values true.
So, true or false will return true and true will return true, but false or false, this false.
Not just negates what you already have. So, if a is true, then not a is false.
And you can also use these things in combination and make sure that you maintain the order that you want with parentheses.
So, I can say, you know, true and true or false. And that will return true.